Guide to the Lester Wunderman Papers, 1946-2010 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1946-2000 and undated, (17 boxes)
  - Articles, 1969-1999
    - Direct Marketing: Past, Present and Future, 1995 (Box 43)
    - Direct Marketing: Una nueva revolution in las ventas, Alta Dirección, 1969 Nov.-Dec. (in Spanish) (Box 43)
    - Direct Marketing, International Encyclopedia of Communications, 1984 (Box 43)
    - DMA Insider article, 1997, (2 folders) (Box 43)
    - Editor and Publisher article, 1978 Apr. (Box 43)
    - I Predict, Printer's Ink, 1964 (Box 43)
    - Innovations and New Problems in Today's Direct Marketing, Direct Marketing, 1975 Nov. (Box 43)
    - Interactive Communications: The Dream and the Reality, Journal of Direct Marketing, 1994 Summer, (3 folders: one folder removed to Oversize Materials Box OV9) (Box 44)
    - Le vente directe--un avenir prometteur, Communication et Langages, 1971 June, Sept. (in French), (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Direct Marketing: Where It's Been And Where It's Going, Madison Avenue, 1977 May (Box 44)
    - Magazines--The Passionate Connection, Signature, 1971 Nov. (Box 44)
    - [Mail Order--The Coming Revolution in Marketing, Advertising Age, 1967 July 24: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV9] (Box 44)
    - Mail Order: The Coming Revolution in Marketing, The Reporter of Direct Mail Advertising, 1967 June (Box 44)
    - Marketing in the Postpresent, Fortune, 1999 (Box 44)
    - Media International article, 1985 Apr. (Box 44)
    - New Frontiers in Direct Marketing, Direct Marketing, 1993 Dec. (Box 44)
    - New Frontiers of Direct Marketing, Jahrbuch Direktmarketing, 1994 (Box 44)
    - New York Times article, 1971 June, (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Preface to Murray Roman, Telephone Marketing, 1976, (2 folders) (Box 44)
    - Preparing for a Consumer-Driven Marketing World, Circulation Management, 1997 Feb. (Box 44)
    - [The In-home Shopping Kid: Tomorrow's Champ?, Frozen Food Age, 1994 June: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV9] (Box 44)
  - Book File
    Includes correspondence, drafts and proofs, edited versions, and reviews relating to Wunderman's book Being Direct: Making Advertising Pay
    - Administrative Files, 1983-1997
      - Book contract, 1983-1994, (2 folders; one folder removed to Oversize Materials Box OV9) (Box 45)
      - Book expenses, 1995-1996 (Box 45)
      - Hans Gedda correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 45)
      - Miscellaneous, 1988-1996 (Box 45)
      - Press kit materials, 1993-1996 (Box 45)
      - Publicity, 1996, (2 folders) (Box 45)
      - Quotes about book, 1997 (Box 45)
      - Random House, 1986-1987 (Box 45)
      - Random House, 1995-1996, (3 folders) (Box 46)
      - Reader comments, 1996-1997, (4 folders) (Box 46)
      - Reviews, 1996-1997, (2 folders) (Box 46)
      - USPS Ad Mail campaign, autographed copy of Being Direct: Making Advertising Pay, 1997 (Box 46)
    - Drafts and Proofs, 1984-1996 and undated
      - American Express section, 1987 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 47)
      - Appendix and footnotes, 1996, (3 folders) (Box 47)
      - Book draft, 1986 (Box 47)
      - Book notes, undated (Box 47)
      - Book roughs--corrections, 1986, (4 folders) (Box 47)
      - Columbia House record club section, 1987, (6 folders) (Box 48)
      - E. Marona's last draft of first part of book, undated (Box 48)
      - How to Start an Advertising Agency section, 1987, (2 folders) (Box 48)
      - International chapter, undated, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 48)
      - International chapter (continued), undated, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 49)
      - Jackson & Perkins section
        - Beth Rogers PhD thesis, Succession in American Rose-Growing Firms: A Study of Process in Commercial Polities, 1990, (2 folders) (Box 49)
        - Changes made after Ken Tach, undated (Box 49)
        - Roughs, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 49)
      - John Stevenson drafts, 1987 Feb. (Box 49)
      - Latest version for correction, 1986 July (Box 49)
      - LW and SCW revision of first part of book, 1987 May, (2 folders) (Box 49)
      - LW book first version, 1984-1993, (5 folders) (Box 50)
      - Manuscript version, 1987, (3 folders) (Box 50)
      - Manuscript with edits, second part, 1988, (3 folders) (Box 51)
      - Manuscript with Jason's edits and corrections, undated, (2 folders) (Box 51)
      - Manuscript with notations, undated, (2 folders) (Box 51)
      - Manuscript written in France, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 51)
      - Originals, first part of book, 1987 May-June, (2 folders) (Box 51)
      - Originals, pages 252-380, 1987 (Box 52)
      - Revised roughs, pages 252-380, 1987 (Box 52)
      - Revised version, EV office copy, 1988, (3 folders) (Box 52)
      - Revisions and copy of manuscript, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 52)
      - Revisions made, Summer 1987 (Box 52)
      - Sackheim section, originals and revisions, 1987 (Box 52)
      - Second part written in France, 1986, (2 folders) (Box 52)
    - Research Files 1946-1995 and undated
      - General--articles, clippings, etc., 1985-1995, (4 folders) (Box 53)
      - American Express
        - General, 1986-1994, (6 folders) (Box 53)
        - American Express: The Companion Card pitch, 1986 Dec.1 (Box 54)
        - Board of Directors meeting, 1995 Oct. 24 (Box 54)
        - Briefings, 1986 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 54)
        - Clippings and press, 1991-1994 (Box 54)
        - Corporate Card, 1987-1994, (4 folders) (Box 54)
        - Direct marketing examples, 1987 and undated (Box 54)
        - Investment Managers account direction, 1989 Mar. 27 (Box 54)
        - Optima Canada, 1990-1994 (Box 54)
        - Optima Card, 1986-1987, (3 folders) (Box 55)
        - Optima Card acquisition campaign mail plan, 1987-1988, (2 folders) (Box 55)
        - Report to Young & Rubicam Board of Directors, 1988 Sept. 27 (Box 55)
        - Targeted Relationship Marketing, 1986-1989 (Box 55)
        - TRS Management Meeting, 1994 (Box 55)
      - Casper Pinsker and Max Sackheim, 1946-1958 (Box 55)
      - Columbia House record club, 1983-1987 (Box 55)
      - Dante's Inferno quote, undated (Box 55)
      - Ford (Box 56)
        - General, 1978-1988, (5 folders) (Box 56)
        - Ford Britain, undated (Box 56)
        - Lincoln-Mercury, 1979-1988, (4 folders) (Box 56)
        - Merkur-Scorpio, 1987 and undated (Box 57)
      - International
        - Australia, 1973-1976 (Box 57)
        - France, 1969-1971, (3 folders) (Box 57)
        - Germany, 1970-1972, (2 folders) (Box 57)
        - Miscellaneous, 1968-1994 (Box 57)
        - United Kingdom, 1964-1970 (Box 57)
      - Magazines
        - Fortune, 1978-1993 (Box 57)
        - Miscellaneous, 1983-1989 (Box 57)
        - Money, 1974-1979, (2 folders) (Box 58)
        - Sports Illustrated, 1975-1994, (3 folders) (Box 58)
        - Time, 1974-1994, (6 folders) (Box 58)
        - [Time: Newspaper/Television/Magazine Campaign Analysis of Results, 1976 Spring: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV9] (Box 58)
        - [Time: Television Cost Factors Per Thousand Newspaper Circulation in the Top 120 ADI's, 1975 July 3: Removed to Oversize Materials Box OV9] (Box 58)
        - Time, Inc. magazines (Time, Fortune, Money, Sports Illustrated), 1974-1978 (Box 58)
  - Writings--Restricted Files, 1997-2000
    - Adweek review and response, 1997 (Box 59)
    - Barnes & Noble, 2000 (Box 59)
    - Book distribution by Lester Wunderman, 1997-1998 (Box 59)
    - Book in Lester Wunderman LLC, 1997 (Box 59)
    - Book purchases, 1997, (2 folders) (Box 59)
    - Chinese edition, 1997-1999 (Box 59)
    - Foreign rights, 1997 (Box 59)
    - Fred Newell, quotes from book, 1999-2000 (Box 59)
    - IBM Ultimate Book Club, 1997 (Box 59)
    - Japanese rights, 1997-1998 (Box 59)
    - Paperback edition, 1997-1999 (Box 59)
    - USPS Ad Mail campaign, 1997 (Box 59)
- Memorabilia, 1957-1988 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Includes plaques, trophies, certificates and other commemorative items and awards.
  - American Chamber of Commerce in Japan, Distinguished Service, 1985 (Box 60)
  - Burson-Marsteller, Certificate of Enlightenment, 1981 (Box 61)
  - Direct Mail Advertising Association, Certificate of Honor, 1960 (Box 61)
  - Direct Marketing Association, 20-year membership, 1985 (Box 61)
  - Direct Marketing Association, 24th Spring Conference, undated (Box 61)
  - Direct Marketing Association of New York, Appreciation, 1983 (Box 61)
  - Direct Marketing Association of New York, Appreciation, 1986 (Box 61)
  - Direct Marketing Club of Southern California, Appreciation, 1988 (Box 62)
  - Direct Marketing Creative Group, John Caples Creative Contest, 1980 (Box 62)
  - Financial Communications Society, Appreciation, 1987 (Box 62)
  - Kansainväliseen Young & Rubicam, Profit Day, 1986 (Box 62)
  - Mail Advertising Club of New York, Appreciation, 1957 (Box 63)
  - VIII Simposio de Marketing Directo, Appreciation, 1988 (Box 63)
  - Young Presidents Organization, Membership, 1961 (Box 64)
- Oversize Materials, (10 boxes)
  Includes large-format items removed from previous series.
  - Dogon Art
    - Article in Life, 1966 June 3 (Box OV1)
    - Scrapbook, 1973-1975 (Box OV1)
  - Meetings and Travel
    - Lonsdale Wunderman (London), 1969 Mar. 6 (Box OV1)
  - Metropolitan Museum
    - Primitive Wing, 1982 (Box OV1)
  - Printed Material
    - Flair, 1950 Apr., Aug. (Box OV1)
    - Scrapbooks of newspaper reprints, Ev'ry Month, 1897 Apr. 1, and 1961 reprint of 1861 Harper's Weekly, (2 scrapbooks) (Box OV2)
  - Publicity
    - Articles
      - Advertising Age, 1993 Oct. (Box OV3)
      - Anuncios (Spain), 1995 June (Box OV3)
      - Børsen (Denmark), 1996 Jan. (Box OV3)
      - Campaña (Spain), 1995 June (Box OV3)
      - Chicago Tribune/New York times, 1978 (Box OV3)
      - Dentsu Journal/Telemarketing Journal (Japan), 1994 Apr. (Box OV3)
      - Direct (book excerpt), 1996 Nov. (Box OV3)
      - Direct, 1998 Mar. (Box OV3)
      - Direct, 1999 Feb. (Box OV3)
      - Direktmarketing (Germany), 1990 (Box OV4)
      - DM News, 1994 May 9 (Box OV4)
      - Economie (Belgium), 1996 May (Box OV4)
      - Financial Times, 1990 Apr. (Box OV4)
      - IP Mark (Spain), 1995 June (Box OV4)
      - La Vanguardia (Spain), 1995 Aug. (Box OV4)
      - Life cover article Mail Order Man of the Year, 1967 Mar. 3 (Box OV4)
      - Marketing Magazine (Canada), 1994 Nov. (Box OV4)
      - Marketing Magazine (Canada), 1997 Nov. (Box OV4)
    - Interviews
      - Direct Marketing News, 1995 Dec. (Box OV4)
      - Direct Marketing News, 1996 Jan. (Box OV4)
      - DM News, 1996 Feb. (Box OV4)
      - Marketing Magazine (Canada), 1995 Nov. (Box OV4)
      - Stratégies (France), 1980 May (Box OV4)
      - Stratégies (France), 1992 Oct. (Box OV4)
      - Wunderama, 1997 May (Box OV4)
  - Samples of Direct Marketing
    - Encyclopedia Americana, 1962 (Box OV5)
    - American Express, 1989 (Box OV6)
    - American Recording Society, circa 1951 (Box OV6)
    - Baron Philippe de Rothschild SA, 1976 (Box OV6)
    - Champion Papers, 1980 (Box OV6)
    - Columbia House record club, 1965-1966 (Box OV6)
    - Famous Artists School, 1957 (Box OV6)
    - Famous Writers School, 1960-1961, (3 folders) (Box OV6)
    - Lincoln-Mercury, 1988-1989, (3 folders) (Box OV7)
    - Literary Guild, 1967-1969, (3 folders) (Box OV7)
    - Time-Life Books, 1964-1965, 1989 (Box OV7)
  - Speeches
    - 1967 June, American Association of Newspaper Representatives (Box OV8)
    - 1971 Feb., Direct Marketing Day (Box OV8)
    - 1977 Apr., Managers Meeting (Box OV8)
    - 1978 Apr., American Association of Advertising Agencies (Box OV8)
    - 1978 Nov., Young & Rubicam Arizona meeting (Box OV8)
    - 1978 Dec., Ad Expo (Box OV8)
    - 1979 Aug., Young & Rubicam Executive Committee (Box OV8)
    - 1979 Sept., Direct Marketing/Mail Order Association, (2 folders) (Box OV8)
    - 1981, Frontiers of Direct Marketing (Box OV8)
    - 1983 July, Direct Marketing Day in New York (Box OV8)
    - 1983 Sept., Direct Marketing Association--Miami (Box OV8)
    - 1985 June, Australia speech (Box OV8)
    - 1988 Jan., L.A. Direct (Box OV8)
    - 1993 Apr., Apple--Frontiers of Direct Marketing (Box OV8)
    - 1993 Oct., Direct Marketing Association--Toronto (Box OV8)
    - 1994 June, DRTV-94, London (Box OV8)
    - 1995, Canada Postal conference (Box OV8)
    - 1996 Oct., Direct Marketing Association--New Orleans (Box OV8)
  - Writings
    - Articles
      - Book Promotion Can Sell More Books Caspar Pinsker Advertising, circa 1940s (Box OV9)
      - Interactive Communications: The Dream and the Reality, Journal of Direct Marketing, 1994 (Box OV9)
      - Mail Order--The Coming Revolution in Marketing, Advertising Age, 1967 July 24 (Box OV9)
      - The In-home Shopping Kid: Tomorrow's Champ?, Frozen Food Age, 1994 June (Box OV9)
    - Book File
      - Administrative--Book contract, 1983-1994 (Box OV9)
      - Research--Magazines--Time: Newspaper/Television/Magazine Campaign Analysis of Results, 1976 Spring (Box OV9)
      - Research--Magazines--Time: Television Cost Factors Per Thousand Newspaper Circulation in the Top 120 ADI's, 1975 July 3 (Box OV9)
  - Large Oversize
    - General
      - Christmas card design layout, undated (Box OV10)
      - Photograph, European site, undated (Box OV10)
      - Photograph, Sugapmach, 1978 June (Box OV10)
      - Photograph, wedding, undated circa 1970s (Box OV10)
      - Print, Nymphenburg, undated (Box OV10)
    - Dogon Art
      - Dogon World children's catalog, undated (Box OV10)
      - Photograph, Dogon sculpture, undated (Box OV10)
      - Photograph, Lester Wunderman in Africa, circa 1970s (Box OV10)
      - Print, African art, undated (Box OV10)
      - Print returned from Viking, used in Laude, Art of the Dogon, undated (Box OV10)
    - Samples of Direct Marketing
      - Hydromix (Doggett-Pfeil Co.), Maxwell Sackheim agency, circa 1940s (Box OV10)
- Audiovisual Materials 1965-1988 and undated, (6 boxes)
  Includes audiocassettes, videocassettes, 16mm and 35mm films.
  Restrictions on Access: Original audiovisual materials are closed to researchers until use copies can be made. Contact Research Services for more information.
  - Originals
    - Audiocassettes
      - Africa Trip (Box AV1)
        - 1. Arrival in Dakar 12/27/75. 2. Press Conference 12/29/75 (Box AV1)
        - 3. Suzanne Senghor 12/30/75. 2. Nianing 1/1/76 Suzanne and Singe (Box AV1)
        - 7. Arrival at Sanga. 8. Arrival at Sanga? (Box AV1)
        - 9. Wedding Sanga. 10. Visit Hogan (Box AV1)
        - 11. Singing at Ogobara's. 12. Singing at Ogobara's (Box AV1)
        - 15. Dance-Sanga. 16. Blank tape (Box AV1)
      - Presentations
        - ATT-DMMA presentation White Plains 3/27/80, Tape 1 (Box AV1)
        - ATT-DMMA presentation White Plains 3/27/80, Tape 2 (Box AV1)
        - HBO 7/18 (Box AV1)
        - HBO 7/27 (Box AV1)
        - Merrill Lynch (Box AV1)
        - Merrill Lynch Original (Box AV1)
        - Minstrel/NARA System presentation (Box AV1)
        - Rehearsal of General Cigar presentation by L. Wunderman (Box AV1)
        - Spiegel #1 meeting, Chicago 2/9/78 (Box AV1)
        - Spiegel #2 meeting, Chicago 2/9/78 (Box AV1)
        - Tape of meeting at Merrill Lynch 11/28 transcribed (Box AV1)
        - Time-Life research used in Tarrytown speech? (Box AV1)
        - U.S. Commission (Box AV1)
      - Speeches by Wunderman
        - Confronting Today's Challenges in the Direct Marketing Ring (Box AV1)
        - Direct Marketing Concepts (Box AV1)
        - Direct Marketing for National Advertiser (Box AV1)
        - Direct Marketing Idea Exchange (Box AV1)
        - Direct Marketing/Mail Order Association, 1979 Oct. (Box AV1)
        - Frontiers of Direct Marketing (Box AV1)
        - Future of Direct Marketing (Box AV1)
        - Keynote Address Chicago, March 83 (Box AV1)
        - Look at Direct Marketing in 1990s (Box AV1)
        - Mail Order Becoming Predictive vs. Reactive Science (Box AV1)
        - Planning Future Strategies, Business to Business, 1982 (Box AV1)
        - Save the Children talk (Box AV1)
        - Service Postaux Europeens Part 1 (Box AV1)
        - Service Postaux Europeens Part 2 (Box AV1)
        - The Art of the Dogon (Box AV1)
        - Tips to Avoid Advertising Pitfalls 9/17/83 (Box AV1)
        - Using the New Marketing Weapons (Box AV1)
        - What Makes Consumers Buy by Mail? (Box AV1)
      - Speeches by others
        - Announcement of Direct Marketing Man of the Year Award Luncheon Address: Dr. Isaac Asimov (Box AV1)
        - Acquisition of Schwab/Beatty by Marsteller Boon to Marketing Efficiency (Box AV1)
        - Direct Marketing at Ogilvy & Mather is Part of Every Major Marketing Plan (Box AV1)
        - Direct Marketing Club of Southern California-- Joseph Sugarman (Box AV1)
        - Direct Marketing to Play Greater Role in Y&R Client Plan--Edward N. Ney (Box AV1)
        - Keynote--Donald V. Seibert (Box AV1)
        - Olympic Coin Story 1976--Austin Page (Box AV1)
        - Targeting For Advantage--Robert Crandall (Box AV1)
      - Tape/Recorder set
        - The Sixties in Sound and Fury (5 tapes) (Box AV1)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Brad Bentz: Telephone Sale (Time-Life Gardening Books 1978) (Box AV1)
        - Communications Audit (Reginald Watts and Derek Bloom of Marsteller) (Box AV1)
        - Discussion of Bond Coupon, 1979 (Box AV1)
        - Ford telephone tape, 12/79 (Box AV1)
        - Franklin Mint (60 Minutes television program) (Box AV1)
        - George Wiedeman interviews: John Canova, Lester Wunderman (2 copies) (Box AV1)
        - Grey Direct--Career Development, 1981 Feb.2 (Box AV1)
        - La Redoute, 1980 (Box AV1)
        - Mike Williams making telephone calls for Lincoln-Mercury in Chicago about the New Savings, 1980 Jan. 31 (Box AV1)
        - New York Direct Marketing Day Luncheon Awards (Box AV1)
        - Norins tape, 1977 Nov. 7 (Box AV1)
        - Presentation--Soviet Olympics (Box AV1)
        - Third International DMMA Conference, Paris, France, 1976 (Box AV1)
        - Western Union birthday greeting (Box AV1)
        - Untitled tapes (2 copies) (Box AV1)
      - Duplicate tapes (Box AV1)
    - Audiotapes
      - Lester Wunderman speeches (Box AV2)
        - French speech (Box AV2)
        - From Ideas to Results, 1968 (Box AV2)
      - Salk Institute campaign
        - Applause (Box AV2)
        - Carpool/Holmes/Antique (Box AV2)
        - David Niven (Box AV2)
        - Gregory Peck (Box AV2)
        - Louise Fletcher (Box AV2)
        - Mary Tyler Moore (Box AV2)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Marshall McCluhan speech (Box AV2)
        - Herb and Elena, Le Dome, 1965 (Box AV2)
        - Principle of Year (Box AV2)
        - Review of Black Comedy, with Malcolm Cowley and Lester Wunderman (Box AV2)
    - Films
      - Africa Speaks to Me, 16mm film reel and booklet, 1971 (Box AV3)
      - History of the 20th Century, 5 unmounted reels, 35mm B/W (Box AV4)
    - Videocassettes
      - Across the Frontiers. Undated. Format: Umatic. TRT: 60:00 (Box AV5)
      - Across the Frontiers (copy). Undated. Format: Umatic. TRT: 60:00 (Box AV5)
      - Art of the Dogon. 1988. Format: VHS. TRT: 30:00 (Box AV5)
      - AT&T Opportunity Calling. 1986. Format: Umatic. TRT: 9:00 (Box AV5)
      - CBS, Opening of Metropolitan Museum Primitive Wing, tape 1. 1982. Format: Umatic. TRT: 20:00 (Box AV5)
      - CBS, Opening of Metropolitan Museum Primitive Wing, tape 2. 1982. Format: Umatic. TRT: 20:00 (Box AV5)
      - Channel 2 interview with Lester Wunderman. 1975. Format: Umatic. TRT: 60:00 (Box AV5)
      - Channel 13 interview with Lester Wunderman. Undated. Format: Umatic. TRT: 30:00 (Box AV5)
      - In Search of Dark Star, show #4. 1980. Format: Umatic. TRT: 30:00 (Box AV5)
      - Phoenix House Interview, Judy Kuriansky, Channel 2 News at 5. 1984. Format: Umatic. TRT: 6:20 (Box AV5)
      - Profiles: Lester Wunderman, Part I unedited. 1983. Format: Umatic. TRT: 60:00 (Box AV5)
      - Profiles: Lester Wunderman, Part II unedited. 1983. Format: Umatic. TRT: 60:00 (Box AV5)
      - Salvadore Dali film to tape transfer. 1977. Format: Umatic. TRT: 45:00 (Box AV6)
      - Time Magazine Selected Direct Response TV Commercials. 1978-1979. Format: VHS. TRT: 26:00 (Box AV6)
      - Tressider/Wunderman Monte Carlo videotape. 1981. Format: Umatic. TRT: 20:00 (Box AV6)
      - Views and Reviews, Lester Wunderman WNET/13 interview. 1980. Format: Umatic. TRT: 10:00 (Box AV6)